<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collonel James Hays speech to the Parlament upon the debate concerning toleration. As it was taken by Anonimus a Member of the House, and sent to the press with this epigram on the author. [dagger] Fælix fifa suis cælebrata Catonibus eheu! clodius in miseros furit, &amp; Catalina Britannos. [dagger] Henderson ...</title>
            <author>Carlisle, James Hay, Earl of, ca. 1612-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E828_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862814</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 126:E828[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Collonel James Hays speech to the Parlament upon the debate concerning toleration. As it was taken by Anonimus a Member of the House, and sent to the press with this epigram on the author. [dagger] Fælix fifa suis cælebrata Catonibus eheu! clodius in miseros furit, &amp; Catalina Britannos. [dagger] Henderson ...</title>
                  <author>Carlisle, James Hay, Earl of, ca. 1612-1660.</author>
                  <author>Brummet, Christoph.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The dagger in epigram is above the word "Catonibus"; the dagger in the right margin has text following that begins with the word "Henderson", but this text has been crossed out and is illegible in all copies seen.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 20th", "4"; last 5 in imprint date crossed through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COLLONEL <hi>JAMES HAYS</hi> SPEECH TO THE PARLAMENT Upon the Debate concerning TOLERATION.</p>
            <p>As it was taken by <hi>Anonimus</hi> A Member of the Houſe, and ſent to the Preſs with this <hi>EPIGRAM</hi> on the Author.</p>
            <q>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <l>Faelix fifa ſuis caelebrata Catonibus Eheu!</l>
               <l>Clodius in miſeros furit, &amp; Catalina Britannos.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:168061:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168061:2"/>
            <head>Coll: <hi>JAMES HAYS</hi> Speech to the Parlament upon the Debate concerning <hi>TOLERATION.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Olomon</hi> hath a notable advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Prov:</hi> 21.23. <hi>Who keepeth his mouth, and his tongue, keepeth his ſoul from troubles:</hi> and yet my ſpirit whiſpers me in the ear, that whoſoever at this time keepeth his mouth, involveth his ſoul in trouble. To me the Declaration of Jeſus appeareth on the wall, <hi>Mat:</hi> 10.33. <hi>Whoſoever denieth me before men, him will I deny before my father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> the ties of God are upon me, for my ſelf and the people for whom I ſerve here; is not the Lords prerogative? are not the privilidges of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Jeſus Chriſt call'd now in queſtion? if I ſhould hold my peace, how might my ſilence be interpreted? ſuffer me therefore Sir, in all ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168061:3"/> to ſpeak to the matter of your preſent Debate which in it ſelf is of ſo high concernment, and will undoubtedly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove of that conſequence to this Common-wealth, that much of the future peace and happines of the State will depend upon it.</p>
            <p>There hath been much arguing theſe dayes by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone concerning a general <hi>Toleration,</hi> and liberty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> before you can happily diſcern either way in this queſtion; I ſuppoſe you'l find it neceſſary to turn your eye toward Religion, upon which this <hi>Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Indulgence,</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> doth reflect.</p>
            <p>Religion, Sir, is that which ties the mind of Man to God, it is that requires the Princes of the earth to rule in meekneſs, Juſtice, and ſobriety; it's that commands the ſubject to obey with love, and ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity, and that unites the minds of men amongſt themſelves. Hence the unity of bodies, the combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in one politique ſociety, from whence the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of fortunes, the mind ruling the body, and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the intereſt and goods, which three are the only props and pillars of all <hi>States,</hi> and Incorporations in the world. It's a true aphoriſme. <hi>Quibus non unio voluntatum non poteſt eſſe una habitatio:</hi> for as the ſoul rules over the body natural by authority, and proper dominion, and the ſpirit by deputation; ſo doeth Religion the ſoul of the body politique rule over the State ſo abſolutely, that if it be in diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the ſpirit wil doubtleſs be out of frame, and the body in danger.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168061:3"/>
            <p>A ſick ſoul ſir, will diſorder the ſoundeſt ſpirit, the ſtrongeſt body: how often hath it made the feet to precipice the bulk? how often the hands to cut the throat? is it ſo Sir? then what ſhall become of that State where Religion is misframed? O! ſhall not the Rulers rage, and the people miſcarry?</p>
            <p>I beſeech you look narrowly to this, leſt by gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too large a <hi>Toleration</hi> you diſhonour God, and diſorder the State:</p>
            <p>I am far from the opinion of thoſe who aſcribe unto themſelves the diſpenſation, and interpretation of the Law, converting their own wil, into a Law, allowing the world no immediat warrant for their faith, but their ſimple authority: by theſe means changing the company of rationall beleevers into a hive of hooded ſmatterers.</p>
            <p>I do alſo much differ in point of judgment, from theſe, who miſregarding all Law, and Eccleſiaſtick conſtitution, and practiſes, ſtrive to turne the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded chriſtian, the houſhold of faith, into a drove of Rambling untied, untoward Enthuſiaſts. Miſtake me not Sir, I do not reflect in the leaſt, upon any ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded chriſtian, whom in my ſoul I love, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor with my heart. No Sir, of thoſe I mean, of whom it may be ſaid (I fear) they profeſs God with their mouths, but live without him in the world.</p>
            <p>That you may the better decide in this matter, and perfectly diſcern, both what to tolerate, and what to caſt out, I would have you keep a mids betwixt theſe two extreams.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168061:4"/>
            <p>Firſt, Sir let the Law and prior Eccleſiaſtick practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes grounded on that Law be your Rule, otherwiſe you will turn all into Anarchie again, and live at random, aſſure your ſelf, <hi>Si terminos a Deo &amp; naturae conſtitutos tranſiveris, qued ultra eſt infinitum eſt:</hi> No man can tel what you'l not do, for you know that <hi>Dato uno abſurdo infinita ſequntur,</hi> and I fear if you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verleap the Law and practiſe of the Church, there wil be nothing after, but <hi>Scelus ſcelere vindicatum,</hi> One crime made good by another.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Sir, I would have you to try the truth of that Law, the verity of theſe practiſes; theſe <hi>I</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive, will be your beſt guides through this deſert of <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Over all you wil find their was one uniformity in Religion, no ſuch <hi>Toleration,</hi> as is here aimed at, no liberty, no indulgence, as to fundamentals; wil you conſult the unwritten Divine and natural Law? it wil tel you it was ſo <hi>ab initio.</hi> Adviſe with the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Law? the Scriptures, the Law of Nations? and they'l ſhew you it was commanded to be ſo. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at Reaſon? and ſhe wil aſſure you it ought to be ſo. Look into the practiſes of the pureſt, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt, eccleſiaſtick ſoeieties? and they'l declare it was ſo. All which being found, I cannot conceive, why it ought not to be ſo ſtil amongſt you; and the rather, becauſe there is nothing more certain, then all Eccleſiaſtick ſocieties were bounded by Laws, and who is ſo ignorant, as not to know? or ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent as to deny? that every Law hath a double
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168061:4"/> facultie, namely, one ſuaſorie, another obligatorie, By the firſt without the laſt, it differeth nothing from a Counſel. It may as a vertue perſwade, but cannot as a duty oblige. It is the laſt, the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie part that maketh the law, it is the form of the law, and gives it being, and he who affirmitively wil declare ſuch a thing to be a Law, and negatively ſay that law hath no compulſorie power, and that no man ſhall be tied to obedience by penalties, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, he muſt pardon me to tel him he makes no Law at all. I ſpeak this for you Sir, who hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the true Chriſtian Proteſtant reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be the profeſſion of <hi>England:</hi> If you ſhall on the other part declare that none ſhall be compelled thereto by penalties, or otherwiſe, but that all ſhall be protected in the exerciſe of their Religion, though differing in judgment from the publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. In this caſe I deſire to know what you have done? I ſay you have made no law for that profesſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but on the contrary a Law againſt it, for your negative doth cloſely ſtifle your affirmative, and makes that you aimed at for a law to be of no force, but leaves all to a graceleſs libertie.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of all Sir, I conceive it will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to take a view of the generall ſtate of the Church, firſt, (before you come unto the particular Churches,) as it is ſet down in the Revelation of Saint <hi>John,</hi> which was a viſion of the Church, <hi>As it was from the beginning, and ſhall continue to the end of the world.</hi> How ſweet is it to obſerve the order of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168061:5"/> God (in his wil toward the Church,) as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to reveal it to Saint <hi>John!</hi> where you find 1. Seals, 2. Trumpets, 3. Vials: with us, Churches, Laws, Penalties; ſeven Seals opened, ſeven Trumpets blown, ſeven Vials powred forth. To each Church called God gives, and proclaims the law; to the law proclaimed he appends the Anathema, ordains the penalties, denounces Judgment on the Rebellious. And this you wil find verified in the particular ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of the ſeveral Churches in order.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof is the <hi>Archetypical</hi> Church, the Church of Angels. God Sir being <hi>unum, verum, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> the only true Good: and the nature of good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Eſſe ſui diffuſivum:</hi> God in the contemplation of his own goodneſs, did beget in himſelf a deſire to diffuſe it, and make it communicable, and practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which could not be without creatures: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did he create the Archetyp wherin the ſhapes, and Ideas of all things were breathed; and there, and then did he ſend forth the ſpotles intelligences: who doth inhabite that infinite vacuity which is filled with the Majeſty of God, whoſe Religion and work it is to ſing praiſe, honor, and glory to the Jaſper on the Throne, with the rain-bow about him.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Sir,</hi> was the firſt ſeal opened, the firſt myſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry revealed; the firſt Church called by the Lamb even the <hi>Bereſhith,</hi> rhe <hi>principium principians,</hi> the word, and wiſdom of the Father, by whom al things were made. The characters of which Church were: a white horſe, a Crown: and bow: The Enſigns of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168061:5"/> 
               <hi>Candor</hi> Victory and triumph. So was it, and ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a pure, victorious, triumphant, Church. Then was the firſt Trumpet blown, the firſt Viall powred out, the firſt Law proclaimed, the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema appended, the firſt vengeance denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rebels, the authors of diviſion, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the conſtitution of this Church, Sir, there was but one God known by the one great ineffable Name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, One <hi>Sephiroth,</hi> one <hi>Emanation,</hi> one great power, one company of Angels, of one mind, thinking the ſame, and ſinging the like, all things in common amongſt them, none knowing more than other, to none a more ful Viſion of God than the reſt, no place or poſſeſſion peculiar to any, this is the nature of Angels, Sir, thus it was, thus it is, and thus it ſhall bee with theſe bleſſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits for ever and ever.. The name of <hi>toleration</hi> was not known here, hereſie a ſtranger to this happy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, til <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and his tender Conſcience brake forth.</p>
            <p>There is a proverb, which in all Ages of the Church hath been found of univerſal truth; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>that God had never a Church, but the Devill had a Chappel in ſome corner thereof.</hi> Sir, all Religion hath its ſuperſtition, all Doctrine its hereſie, and here it did begin, even in this, the pureſt, and perfecteſt Church that ever was, or ſhal be.</p>
            <p>The Devil emulous of the glory and greatneſs of God, would needs ſet up his own Image, erect a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168061:6"/> of his own, by dividing that bleſſed unity into two, <hi>Right, &amp; wrong, truth, and falſehood.</hi> But what came of it, Sir, was he tolerated? was he ſuffered to go ſo? No, the ſpirit of unity and truth went out againſt him, with crown, and bow? and conquering did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the prince of Darkneſs, caſt him out of the congregation, deprived him the happineſs of Heaven and thurſt him down to Hel, and the earth to have, his dominion amongſt the ſons of Men, hence that Church purchaſed, and ſhall while the world laſts enjoy the name of <hi>Triumphant</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this puniſhment God did not only condemn <hi>toleration;</hi> aſſert the truth, the unity of Worſhip, the entirenes of Religion; clearly holding forth that he would admit of no copartner in the Worſhip, and praiſes of the Angels: but alſo did declare the deteſtable nature of hereſie, and how unſupportable a thing it was: and thus did he by the power of his own Councel which cannot etr, reunite the Church again.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Church was the Paternal church, that whereof <hi>Adam</hi> under God, was Lord, and High Prieſt. In the conſtitution of this church you'l find there was but, One God, one man, one command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one Religion, one way of Worſhipping that God, one treaſure, and common fortune for all, one body to enjoy that fortune, one mind in that body: <hi>Adam</hi> knew none above God, loved none as God, ſerved none but God, feared none beſides God There was no hereſie in Doctrine here, no ſchiſm in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168061:6"/> diſcipline, <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood in need of none to teach him, and as few to enforce him to obey. All was one Sir, an univerſal Oneneſs; this was the firſt, and great model amongſt men.</p>
            <p>Thus was the ſecond Seal opened, the ſecond Myſtery revealed, the ſecond Church called, the Law proclaimed. <hi>Eat not of the Tree of knowledg, &amp;c. Gen:</hi> 2.17. The Anathema appended, <hi>The day thou eateſt thou ſhalt ſurely dye,</hi> comparatively like in every thing to the pattern, the Archetypicall Church, onely differing in the prophetical chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, the red horſe and the ſword, the badges of blood, war, and man-ſlaughter; ſignifying that this Church ſhould be liable to many, and great temptations; and the ſpirit of the times much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to blood, cruelty, and revenge.</p>
            <p>All things here were anſwerable to the pattern til the appearing of <hi>Satan,</hi> and founding of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by him; Then were the characters of this Seal made manifeſt, and read in <hi>Mundo.</hi> The pure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and Trinial unitie, (the prop and pillar of all ſocieties) rent aſunder and all turned to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: Nothing now but blood and War: God againſt man, and man againſt God, Father againſt Son, and Brother againſt Brother, and the Devil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all, and all for Religions ſake. <hi>Adam</hi> was one, and the <hi>Devil</hi> made two, and that was Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: God had a Temple, and now begins Satan to have a Synagogue: God had his Prieſt, and the <hi>Devil</hi> his Chaplain. <hi>Abel</hi> of one mind, <hi>Cain</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168061:7"/> of another, <hi>Cain</hi> draws the ſword, <hi>Abel</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with killed. Thus the unity of mind, the unity of bodies rent in two. <hi>Iſaac</hi> had one portion, and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> had another: <hi>Iſaac</hi> the promiſe, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> what he could gain; his hand againſt all, and all againſt him. Thus came the happy, and harmleſs unity of fortune into the community of poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to be converted into the miſerable, and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Law of property. <hi>Jacob</hi> was of one mind, <hi>Eſau</hi> of another; he choſe the birth-right, even <hi>Sacrum ſacerdotii;</hi> Sir, <hi>Eſaw</hi> ſomwhat elſe, <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Dominium ventriculi,</hi> the poſſeſſions of this Earth, the things of this world. Nay look over the whole Paternal time, even from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes;</hi> youl find nothing but hereſie in doctrine, and ſchiſm and diviſion in the matter of worſhip. The impreſſion of the red horſe ſeconded with War, blood, and wounds. The miſerable effects of the tearing ſword: And yet throughout al, not one word of <hi>Toleration,</hi> ſtil he who chooſes the better part, and adhears to the unity and purity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, goes away with a bleſſing; and the other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively, or by conſequence loaded with a curſe. <hi>Adam</hi> is puniſhed, <hi>Eve</hi> plagued, the devil condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: though there was neither man nor woman in the world beſides, yet would not the Lord away with the breach of his Law; the queſtioning of his fundamentals, no <hi>toleration</hi> in theſe Sir, no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, no indulgence, no by-worſhip allowed; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> approved, <hi>Cain</hi> baniſhed, <hi>Iſaac</hi> choſen, <hi>Iſhmael</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168061:7"/> caſt out, <hi>Noah</hi> ſaved, the world drowned, <hi>Lot</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and <hi>Sodom</hi> burnt, and ſo forth over the whole Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of that Church, you ſhal find the ſignals of love towards the one, and the tincture of his wrath and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation cleaving faſt to the other.</p>
            <p>The third Church, Sir, was the National Church, called of God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the third Seal opened, the third Myſtery revealed, the Church called, the Law proclaimed, the third Anathema appended, conform to the firſt plot in every thing, except the characters, <hi>viz.</hi> the black horſe, the pair of ballances, intituling on this ſociety the dead, and lingring works of the Law, much ſelfiſhneſs and home love flowing from the niceneſs of property, and affection to intereſt, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioning much contempt of the Law of God, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of his glory. All which you may obſerve in the conſtitution of that Church, and progreſs therof.</p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Moſes</hi> ſummons it by ſhewing the people he was come from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to call them to the worſhip of him who is, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he ſetleth fundamentals, and declares the Law, as you may find <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. from 2. to 21 verſe, where he inſtituteth the Paſſeover, and feaſt of unlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened bread.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. He addeth the Anathema, the Segregetur, no ſtranger ſhall eat thereof, as <hi>verſe</hi> 43. no forraigner, no hired ſervant, as <hi>verſe</hi> 45; the penaltie may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly collected from that of the tabernacle, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> 5 <hi>And every ſtranger that draweth nigh ſhall ſurely dye,</hi> and more fully <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.15, and 19. <hi>See, I have ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168061:8"/> thee this day, life and good, death and evill.</hi> And more clearly he tels the people that if they would fear the Lord, and keep his ſtatutes, they ſhould be bleſſed, and poſſeſs the Land, but if otherwiſe, they ſhould periſh, and be accurſed for ever. Suffer me to make a little digreſſion; it ſhall be ſhort, and to good purpoſe I hope.</p>
            <p>Sir, you know it is, and hath been the care, nay I may ſay, the ambition of all maſters of Arts, ſciences, and ſocieties to reduce theſe arts, ſciences, and ſocieties, to the pureſt perfection; neither is this perfection they aim at (let them think what they will) an imaginarie one, or of their own invention (if they do, they are in an error, no Sir, it is that pure, and primitive perfecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on which was in all arts, ſciences, and ſocieties, and in which all arts, ſciences, and ſocieties were at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: for there is <hi>nihil novi inter nos:</hi> As to that Sir, it is impoſſible to make things better then once they were: and it ſhould be every ones care to bring them as nigh to the pattern as they can.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Moſes</hi> his practiſe in the beginning of that National Church, he ſtudied to have all of one mind that thereby he might reduce this numerous bulk into one body politick, one Congregation; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently have the goods and fortune as one treaſurie to ſerve and uphold the State. He wel knew that <hi>Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantia inter ſe ſoepe conveniunt in tertio.</hi> And that <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque conveniunt in uno tertio conveniunt inter ſe:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did he begin with the unity of mind, Religion the pole of the State, at which all courſes, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168061:8"/> ſo different on the line, wil meet in the end. He wel knew, that having once (both out of policie and piety) conjured them with Religion, and made them one there, he ſhould eaſily unite their bodies unite their fortunes, and ſo become maſter of all: The mind ruling the body, and the body the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <p>All over the conſtitution of this Church you'l find this triple unitie commanded; and in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs ſtil aimed at, in caſe of defection; I need cite to you for the firſt, onely the manner of celebrating the Paſſeover, and feaſt of nleavened bread, <hi>Exod:</hi> 12. from 43 upward, where</p>
            <p>Firſt is ſhown who ſhall be admitted, namely, all the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> either by birth, or conſequence. By Birth, as the Congregation <hi>verſe</hi> 47. by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, The circumciſed ſtranger, <hi>v:</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to prevent <hi>Toleration,</hi> or any Debate thereabout, is declared who ſhall not be admitted, <hi>No ſtranger, no forreigner, no hired ſervant, ver:</hi> 43. and 45. <hi>No Heretick, no Schiſmatick?</hi> None but he that wil ſubmit to the bloody law of circumciſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, is ſhown the manner how this feaſt was to be celebrated, 1. In one houſe, 2. No fleſh to be carried without doors, 3. No bones broken.</p>
            <p>By all which you ſee, how that firſt hee'l have them of one mind in profeſſion, acknowledging the one true God, and him only; of one mind in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, hee'l be adored in the accuſtomed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded manner, all muſt be circumciſed. 2. Hee'l
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168061:9"/> have them of one body, under the name of a <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> ruled by one Law, as ver: 49. Thirdly, hee'l have them of one fortune, as it were, by meeting in one houſe, once every year, and eating of one diſh together, And while they are together, hee'l have them neither to carry fleſh without doors, nor break a bone: ſhewing he would have no diviſion, no Hereſies amongſt them, that he would own no temporary profeſſors, no livery-men, no pettie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers abroad: Peremptorily ſaying, no uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed perſon ſhal eat thereof: No <hi>Toleration,</hi> on any terms. This was but a ſmal comfort to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, whoſe ſqueemiſh, and tender ſtomachs could eat no Lamb with the Congregation of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> in the houſe of God; and yet perhaps they had an appetite to devour Swines fleſh with the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> in <hi>Bethaven,</hi> the houſe of iniquity.</p>
            <p>The ſecond remarkable paſſage againſt this <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> is, the giving of the Law at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> where you find the command of keeping the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath to be ſo very ſtrict, that the very ſtranger with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the gates is bound thereby. This (I beleive) looks liker compulſion then <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third, and ſingularly obſervable thing in that Church againſt <hi>Toleration,</hi> is to be ſeen in the great and marvellous fabrick of the Tabernacle. Let no man think that this was a bare peice of Artifice, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying no more then what was ſeen. It were ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to think that God would have kept <hi>Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 40 dayes in the Mount, only to learn to build an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168061:9"/> houſe, which any ingenious artiſt could have learned in one day (<hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe) from a more unskilful maſter than was he who taught <hi>Moſes.</hi> No, it did containe within it the true myſtery of all things betwixt <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi> God had ſaid, <hi>Oſtendam tibi omne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> And there he made good his promiſe. For in the Mount he gave him a full ſight of the Archetype; and he commands him to build this houſe according to all that he ſaw in the Mount. I do eſteem it high arrogancy to think that the ſmalleſt pin thereof wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome notable ſymbole or other: which, were it ſuitable for this time, and this place, I ſhould preſume to evince by undeniable arguments; now I ſhall only ſpeak ſo far as relates to the preſent purpoſe now in hand.</p>
            <p>Seldome fals it out, that a skilful maſter builder contrives for his own houſe rooms which are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous: And can we be bold to think, that the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God of infinite wiſdom who framed all, hath put any thing unto this artifice of his without a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this Tabernacle</hi> it is obſervable that it was al divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three, 1: <hi>Structure,</hi> 2ly <hi>Apparate,</hi> 3ly. <hi>Salva guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> or the <hi>Temple militia.</hi> Again the ſtructure alſo into three, 1 <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum,</hi> 2 <hi>The room for the Altar and ſacificing Levites,</hi> 3 <hi>The porch of the Temple or the Court of the Congregation.</hi> Obſerve that the firſt was made of Gold, the ſecond of Shittim wood, and the third of courſer materials yet. In the <hi>Apparat</hi> alſo three, 1. <hi>The Ark, the mercy ſeat, and cherubims</hi> for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168061:10"/> the firſt room, 2 The Altar, the candleſticks, the table, for the ſecond, 3 Hangings, pillars, ſockets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the third.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, Sir, that the firſt room and furniture was neither ſeen, nor frequented by the people, but by the high Prieſt alone, and that once a year. The ſecond room was ſeen, but not frequented by the people. Sir, it was the ſervice of the Prieſts to offer daily ſacrifice there. The third room, Sir, was both ſeen, &amp; frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the people daily. By the firſt is ſignified (as to us) the plentifull myſteries of Jeſus Chriſt, who is both <hi>Arca</hi> and <hi>Arcus,</hi> the Ark and the Rainbow: The mercy ſeat, and cherubims being the word in the two Teſtaments, betwixt which God is pleaſed to reveale himſelf to the world. Theſe Sir, are <hi>ſecretiora ſacra,</hi> which muſt not be medled with, muſt not be called into queſtion: None are allowed, none are ſuffered to doubt of the <hi>Deity,</hi> the <hi>Unity in Trinity,</hi> the <hi>Incarnation, Birth, Life, Transfiguration Death, Reſurrection, Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and glorification of the Word;</hi> theſe with ſeverall others are ſuch as may not be denied upon any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whatſoever</p>
            <p>By the ſecond room and things therin, are ſignified the holy Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, The adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word and Sacraments; which may be ſeen, but not frequented by the people, they are to look on them with a reverend eſteem. It is the charge of the Prieſts to be here, and to diſpenſe them to the people, theſe are the Jewels of the Goſpel, which though the people do often ſee and taſte, yet muſt they not be trampled upon by the Canaile.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168061:10"/>
            <p>The third room, and things therein were yet more courſe, daily ſeen, daily frequented by the people, ſuch are the motions of the ſpirit in our hearts, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on us by frequenting the word and ſacraments. Here is a proper place, a peculiar way of exerciſe allotted for thoſe who are thus inſpired: the place The Porch of the Temple: The Subject of their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Congregation, the time, Always<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate, inſpired Laicks, are to exerciſe their gift upon all men, at all times, by a good and exemplary life and converſation. And not at firſt hand to invade the Prieſts charge; the holy things of the Altar, to which they are and ought to be but ſtrangers. And if they will at it, <hi>brevi manu,</hi> upon pretence of <hi>toleration</hi> and liberty to tender Conſciences: then let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what was done to <hi>Saul</hi> for ſacrificing in <hi>Samuels</hi> abſence 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 13.14. <hi>Was not his Kingdome torn from him?</hi> was <hi>Saul</hi> a King thus dealt with? what think you then ſhal become of <hi>A?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the mention that I find in the Tabernacle of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration,</hi> is; <hi>And the ſtranger that comes nigh ſhal ſurely dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing I mentioned of the Tabernacle was the <hi>Salva guarda,</hi> the Militia, and that you have alſo in three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Secular guards, the bands of <hi>Juda, Ruben, Iſſachar, Gad, &amp;c.</hi> 2ly. Spiritual guards, the ſquadrons of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonits, Cohathites,</hi> and <hi>Merarits,</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. The authority of both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> within all: Thus was the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle guarded, and the ſtranger that came nigh was to dye,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168061:11"/> what think you had become of that people, and that houſe, if thoſe guards <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> had left their poſts, and laied the holy tabernacle open to the wild boars, the uncircumciſed Nations?</p>
            <p>In ſumm Sir, this Tabernacle was a type of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods works in nature, and of his ſpirit in the Church: You ſee there was in it a great variety of many pieces, whereof every one was indented in another. The whole ſtanding in one conjunction. You are the boords whereof the myſtical tabernacle is framed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.2. This is that wherof <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.20. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee Jeruſalem a taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle which never ſhal be removed</hi> And whoſoever is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynted, he canot be within the tabernacle. We read <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.15. of Veſſels which if they lay open or uncovered were to be accounted unclean You are the Veſſels of the holy and heavenly tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, framed by the hand of the omnipotent potter whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. ſaith. <hi>Alia vaſa in hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, alia in contumeliam.</hi> If you be not cloſe and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among your ſelves, but ſhaken aſunder into pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, you are the contumelious veſſels of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>Were it not to ſurpriſe your time, <hi>Sir,</hi> I could evidence much of the mind of God againſt Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on manifeſted by his Judgments upon the uſurpers of liberty: the vilipenders of the Law in the days of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, Joſhua, Judges, Kings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Prophets</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Why ſhould I mention the abomination of God, the calf of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> the rebellion of <hi>Core?</hi> the avarice of <hi>Achan?</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168061:11"/> The Apoſtacy of the new Generation of Iſrael after <hi>Joſhua?</hi> and the Elders ſerving <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth?</hi> Their worſhipping the Gods of <hi>Syria, Zidon,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab? Sauls</hi> ſacrificing in abſence of <hi>Samuel? Uzziah</hi> his touching the Ark? <hi>Ahabs</hi> covenant with <hi>Benhadad?</hi> The building of Altars, erecting of groves and high places by the wicked Kings of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> upon all whom their iniquity did heavily fall, and the wrath of God eminently appear.</p>
            <p>It is ſingularly remarkable, Sir, that the remnant of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who (after the death of <hi>Gedaliah</hi> at <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pah</hi> went into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and did rebel againſt <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to worſhip the Hoaſt of Heaven. That they ſtudied to convince him with reaſon, and that by two argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 1. When we did ſo before we had bread to eat: 2ly, and our Heads did it with us, that is our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and leaders, <hi>Jer:</hi> 44 17. But neither reaſon nor authority can ſatisfie, for <hi>Jer: v</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23 confeſſeth that it was ſo, but replies, and did not God meet with you? he did, for is not Aegypts deſtruction clearly prophecied for their ſake <hi>ch:</hi> 46. What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved liberty here, Sir? <hi>Ilias malorum,</hi> a gulf of evils.</p>
            <p>Over all this Church you'l find nothing like <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which if it could have been granted to any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or congregated number in the world, ſure it had been to the beloved houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And yet we find, that once upon their Rebellion, God was about to have extinguiſhed the very name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and made a Nation of <hi>Moſes, Numb:</hi> 12.12. And another time upon the like rebellion, God condemns them to 40
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168061:12"/> years wandring, and ſuffered none that rebelled ever to enter the promiſed Land.</p>
            <p>If any one perſon might have been diſpenſed with in this matter, ſure it had been <hi>Moſes</hi> the Lords fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar acquaintance, and yet, for but one blow more than enough, he was blown out of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he ſee it, but never came into it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Was it ſo with the choſen <hi>Iſrael?</hi> with the great <hi>Moſes?</hi> whom neither authority, nor State neceſſity could excuſe, O what ſhall become of the reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gentiles, if we fall into the like errors? my ſoul doth tremble, to think on the ſad conſequence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertat Deus!</hi> I hope, I hope Sir, the Lord wil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you from this uncovert iniquity! fly the ſin as you would avoid the Judgment.</p>
            <p>I heard an honorable perſon below move, The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ralites ſuffering ſlaves to live amongſt them, as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I humbly conceive, Sir, there is a twofold <hi>tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> a civil <hi>toleration,</hi> and a ſpiritual: for the firſt, Sir, they had indeed, and upon a civil account meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; they ſuffered them to live amongſt them, becauſe they ſerved them to good uſe. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.21. So did they tolerate and cheriſh their horſes and Oxen. As to the ſecond, Sir, they were ſtrangers to it, and it to them. They were neither admitted to the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Iſrael in the Tabernacle; neither were they allowed to ſerve the Gentile Gods after their own faſhion at home. So to this ſpiritual <hi>toleration</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168061:12"/> it was with them as with the beaſts. If this be it, that's pleaded for the ſeperate Saints, In time I ſhall make bold to ſpeak to it.</p>
            <p>It was alſo Objected, what <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.22. <hi>If the Lord be God follow him, if</hi> Baal <hi>follow him,</hi> I hope no man will conclude that this flowed from him as a rule, or as if he meant to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue a <hi>toleration</hi> of the worſhip of <hi>Baal.</hi> No, he ſpoke it by way of reproach, ſhewing what abominable inconſtancy, and deteſtable ingratitude it was, and would prove, to forſake the living God who had done ſo much for them, and their Fathers, and ſerve <hi>Baal,</hi> and his Chemarims.</p>
            <p>It was likewiſe Objected, <hi>Sir,</hi> that we are not now under the Law, and therefore not to be tied by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments raiſed from the Law, We are not indeed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dark Law, the <hi>Typical</hi> law, the Law of works: yet are we under the law of grace, even the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the children of God, which is the ſame in ſubſtance, the old Law was in ſhadow, and which in its ſubſtance is as forcible, and binding now as ever. There was not one tittle of that Law which did not ſignifie ſomething to come, which when it is come, is of ſo much more power as the ſubſtance is above the ſhadow. Chriſt himſelf ſaies <hi>Mat:</hi> 5.17. <hi>That he came not to deſtroy, but to fulfill the Law and till Heaven and earth paſs away, one jot of the Law ſhall not paſs till all be fulfilled; and whoſo breaketh the leaſt of theſe, and teacheth others to do ſo, ſhall be leaſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168061:13"/> in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Now this liberty, The law of the Goſpel, muſt not be miſconſtrued, and taken for, a looſing of all religious bonds and ties. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent which St. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Gal.</hi> 5.13: forbiddeth for to uſe liberty for occaſion to the fleſh, <hi>but for love one to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard another,</hi> and explaineth himſelf <hi>ver.</hi> 19. declaring <hi>the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rks of the fleſh to be adultery, fornication, uncleaneſs,</hi> and ſo forth, and v: 22. <hi>the fruits of the Spirit to be love, joy, peace, &amp;c. againſt which, there is no Law.</hi> We are then ſtill under a Law, witnes <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.12. <hi>So do, and ſo ſpeak, as they that muſt be judged by the Law of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Church is that which now is, the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, the Chriſtian Church, Univerſal, I call it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord came to call the Jew and Gentile to repentance. This Church was called, This myſtery revealed, This ſeal opened by the Lamb, indeed the Lamb inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnate Jeſus Chriſt, the author and finiſher of our faith. The characters of this Church were a pale horſe, and Death, with the ſword, hunger, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and the Beaſts of the earth, to ſignifie, that, this pale and new revived Church, the dead, dark, and lingring letter of the old Law being quickened by the ſpirit, and converted into the light and liberty of the Goſpel, The law of grace, ſhould be begun with death, and continued with perſecutions of ſeverall kinds; the worſt whereof, and the greateſt Enemies to the Church of God, I eſteem to be the foul noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Beaſts of the earth, the children of this world
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168061:13"/> who hatch &amp; maintaine hereſies, Atheiſme and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, the greateſt of all evills, <hi>Ut credant mendacio qui veritati non crediderint,</hi> theſe are the beaſts you have moſt need to be affraid of at this time.</p>
            <p>In this Church you'l find Jeſus the founder of it to have beene of One mind with the Father, and the Father with him; he was of one ſubſtance with the Father, and the Father with him, had no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, all things were common to him. This he leaveth in legacie to his Apoſtles, willing them to be of One mind, and love one another <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.34. A <hi>new commandement give</hi> I <hi>you, that ye love one another, for hereby ſhall ye be known to be my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> He required it alſo as a duty and meane of obedience as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.15. <hi>If you love me, you will keepe my Commandements;</hi> for this ſame u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and love, he prayeth the Father before his death on behalfe of the Apoſtles, <hi>Ioh</hi> 17.11. <hi>that they may be one as we are one.</hi> In the conſtitution of this Church I finde two notable paſſages in order to this ſame Toleration. The one <hi>Luke</hi> 10.11. where ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad his diſciples to preach, he charged them if any Citie refuſe them, to ſhake the duſt of their feet againſt it, a ſad Anathema indeed Sir, if it were rightly conſidered. The other is a ſadder (yet,) from the mouth of Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>If any man deny me before men, him will I deny before my Father in Heaven. Matt.</hi> 10.33. Obſerve Sir, that he who deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the doctrine of Jeſus denyes himſelfe: for he <hi>ſaies whoſoever ſhall breake the leaſt of theſe, &amp;c.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168061:14"/> ſtall be leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> And who offendeth one of theſe little ones, or who refuſeth the works of love to the needy, all you know they are liable to ſeverall ſad Anathemas.</p>
            <p>Will you looke into the pactice of the apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les after Chriſt, and youl finde it was thus with the diſciples and beleivers then alſo, for <hi>Act.</hi> 4.32. it is ſaid; <hi>And the multitude of beleivers were of one heart, one mind, one Soule; neither didany man ſay what he had was his own;</hi> all things weie commond, and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures the <hi>Romans,</hi> 12.5. <hi>that being many they were one bedy in Chriſt, and every one Members one of another.</hi> He exhorts the Corinthians in that 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 13.11. <hi>to be of one mind and live in peace and love</hi> and finally, he telleth the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4.56 <hi>That there is one body, and one Spirit one Lord, one faith one Baptiſme, one God and Father of all,</hi> In all their Councells alſo they were unanimous, for it was for the ſake of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they were called. We muſt not think that they did call Councells to queſtion their own Religion. No, it was <hi>prorenata,</hi> ever upon the occaſion of ſome Schiſme, ſome hereſie, as you will find in all their Councells where their work was to cleare truths and condemne errors, without regard to To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration. In the beeleving and obeying of theſe truths to which there was ever an <hi>Anathema</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, witneſs <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus, let him be Anathema, Maranatha,</hi> alſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. <hi>If</hi> I <hi>or an Angel from Heaven Preach any
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168061:14"/> other Goſpel unto you let him be accurſed.</hi> In all the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles Canons, you'l ever find a <hi>Deponatur</hi> for the Clergy a <hi>Segregetur</hi> for the ſeculars. All men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually tied to the rule without any exception or Latitude at all.</p>
            <p>The firſt Councils they kept was at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the 34 year of our Lord on the occaſion of Electing <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> to ſerve in Lieu of <hi>Judas</hi> the Heretick, and high Prieſt of Satan, Act. 1. where it is worthy obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that before <hi>Matthias</hi> was Elected, &amp; the entire nubmer made up: <hi>Peter</hi> ſheweth the occaſion of their meeting to be the fulfilling, and uniting the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical number, the ſupplying of <hi>Juda's</hi> charge, And next he pronounces an Anathema of the Charge, a ſad one indeed. <hi>Let his habitation be deſolate.</hi> This ſmels nothing of <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Council was at <hi>Jeruſalem, anno</hi> 34, before the death of <hi>Steven,</hi> upon occaſion of a mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muring amongſt the <hi>Grecians</hi> againſt the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> becauſe their Widdows were neglected, <hi>Act:</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The third Council you'l find <hi>Act:</hi> 15. the cauſe was diſſention about Circumciſion.</p>
            <p>The fourth <hi>Councel</hi> is <hi>Act:</hi> 21. Anent the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of legal things for a time. In theſe two laſt there was ſomthing might ſeem to be like to <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration,</hi> for in the third the Gentiles are exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the burden of the Law; by the fourth the Jews are allowed the exerciſe therof. But</p>
            <p>Conſider, Sir, firſt, that theſe things purifying
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168061:15"/> waſhing, ſhaving, were in themſelves no ſin at all; In themſelves I ſay, for if otherwiſe they had been, ſurely <hi>Paul</hi> had neither tolerated nor uſed them, ſin being condemned even in <hi>Caſu neceſſitatis.</hi> There being no excuſe able to waſh away the guilt of ſin. 2ly. Things in themſelves indifferent cannot be uſed at all times without ſin. For it is one thing to tolerate ſomethings in <hi>Eccleſia conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuenda,</hi> another in <hi>Eccleſia conſtituta;</hi> It may be in the one expedient, in the other altogether unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; which flows from the reſpective conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of either.</p>
            <p>Whether the like neceſſity does preſs you now, which urged the Apoſtles then, you beſt know: for my part, I doubt of it: And were it ſo. Yet can I find no warrant in all the Scriptures to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme Gods Name: And I am perſwaded the <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi> now aimed at, will tend to that in the higheſt degree. What madneſs is it that men will be content to be bound up from acting, or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the ſupream Magiſtrate? or the State, under no leſs pain than Treaſon? And who ſo tranſgreſſeth is hailed to the ſtake. And yet will they ſtrugle to unwreath themſelves from the yoak of Chriſt, and under the notion of tender Conſciences muſt needs be tolerated, yea, (why ſay I tolerated?) warranted by a Law to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Would you but enquire at the four great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168061:15"/> univerſally received by all; Namely, that of <hi>Nice</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 323. Conſiſting of 300 Biſhops, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and <hi>Quadradecimals.</hi> That of <hi>Conſtance</hi> againſt the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Hereſie. That of <hi>Epheſus</hi> againſt the <hi>Neſtorian</hi> Hereſie, and that of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> againſt the <hi>Eutychean</hi> hereſie. Enquire I ſay, at theſe, and you ſhall find, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing amongſt them like <hi>Toleration.</hi> Their care and practice was the clearing and aſſerting of truth, and condemning of Error.</p>
            <p>Do not you think, Sir, but theſe ſame errors, or worſe, are amongſt you, which were amongſt them at that time? Is there none, think you, Sir, in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> who will ſay with <hi>Arrius. Dei filius aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do erat, aliquando non erat?</hi> None, who with <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius</hi> holds that <hi>Spiritus ſanctus nihil ad patris &amp; filii divinitatem &amp; gloriam pertinet?</hi> None who maintaineth <hi>Filium eſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>non</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſimilem non ejuſdem eſſentiae?</hi> None think you, who with <hi>Neſtorius</hi> divides the natures of God, and call<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? As if ſhe had brought forth Chriſt as man only, not as God and man. Is it not poſſible to find one who'l ſay, <hi>Chriſtus non ſub carnis veritate, ſed figura in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris laborabat?</hi> Aſſure your ſelf, Sir, there are thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of this nature amongſt you, and worſe, if worſe may be: Nay, (what ſay I may be?) there wants not, who deny that they hold any thing of God, or his Son either, they knowing neither, and denying both; acknowledging nothing above
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168061:16"/> themſelves in dignity, (I mean of Eſſence.) In place they may, and yet with a grudg I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. Looſe the bonds, and break the curb of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and cheriſh ſuch impious vermine as this land ſwarms with; and you ſhall ſee, what will become of your State in the end, when it will be too late to repent. Seeing therefore you have the ſame Enemies.</p>
            <p>In all Humility I adviſe, that you uſe the ſame weapons againſt them which they did with ſo much, and ſo good ſucecſs: otherwiſe ſhew us a better way how to overthrow this monſtrous <hi>Hydra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray you, Sir, the ſweet and gentle voice of <hi>Syon</hi> the peaceful ayr of the Goſpel, The faith of Jeſus, and the principles of Chriſtian Religion; are they not as dear to us the Children of Light, as the dictates of Nature were to the Sons of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> As pretious to the Adopted Gentile, as the fearful voîce of Mount <hi>Sinay,</hi> the Thundring Trumpet, the lingring works, and uncertain Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Law, were to the choſen <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me exhort you therefore, Sir, you who ſits in the chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to take to hart the building of the ſanctuarie! Remember, that ſo ſoone as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were delivered from the bondage of Egypt, the Tabernacle was provided for, <hi>Exod</hi> 25. No ſooner had <hi>David</hi> reſt from his enemies, but he intended the building of a houſe to God, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.1. And a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168061:16"/> the firſt and greateſt of the miracles of Chriſt was the purgeing of the temple, the ſubduing of the enemies and abuſes thereof. Remember that <hi>ſuper hanc potram</hi> even according to all that you have ſeen in the Mount, after the modell of Sion muſt you build your houſe: otherwiſe, if the ſtorme blow your houſe will fall.</p>
            <p>But you'l happily reply, that you have done that already in paſſing a Vote on the 35 Article, and declaring the Chriſtian Religion, to be the profeſſion of <hi>England.</hi> A good beginning (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,) a fair frontiſpiece indeed. But, beware that it prove not like the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Temples, brave ſtately buildings to look upon: but within, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Images of Doggs, Catts, Crocodiles, and unclean Beaſts. I adviſe you, Sir, to provide for this Houſe, and furniſh it according to all that I have told you. The kindlieſt gueſt that ever came into a houſe is the Landlord himſelf. If you do it not, Sir, be ſure your Enemies will do it for you. But what ſay I? do it? I fear they have done done it already.</p>
            <p>UP therefore, and call to mind: that Chriſt did with zeal and paſſion, if any may be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to him, purge the Temple, brake down the the tables, and caſt out the buyers and ſellars. Call your Brother <hi>Aaron,</hi> (whoſe mouth the ord hath
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168061:17"/> filled with Eloquence, and his heart with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) &amp; you with him, and he with you ſcourge out the unapparalled gueſts with the cords of the ſpiritual ſword, and civil execution. Be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to aſſert the truth, nor afraid to condemn er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. And then you'l know both what to Tolerate, and whom to compel. <hi>And this is my humble motion.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
